Finding Aid for David L. Angus Papers 1956-1999
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
David L. Angus Papers 1956-1999
Angus, David L.
Professor of education at the University of Michigan. Biographical information; correspondence; writings and conference papers; course materials; files pertaining to education in China; and photographs.
0214 Aa 2
4 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Anna Angus (donor no. 8878 ) and came to the library in September 1999.
The collection is open for research.
David L. Angus was born December 7, 1933 in Findlay, Ohio. He was educated at Bowling Green State University and Ohio State University, receiving his Ph.D. in 1965. In 1966, he came to the School of Education (SOE) of the University of Michigan where he rose from assistant to associate to full professor in 1973 with a specialty in educational foundations and policy.
In 1985, with the reorganization of the SOE, Angus became more interested in educational administration and policy and began to teach core courses in the school and took a part-time role as associate director for research of the Bureau of Accreditation and School Improvement Studies.
Professor Angus wrote extensively on a wide variety of topics. He was especially interested in the politics of education and the history of curriculum. In addition, Angus was interested in international and comparative education. He made several trips to China, attending conferences and teaching at Peking University and the Chinese University of Hong Kong. In 1992, he was chairman of the year-long international symposium "Nationalism at Risk" that convened at the University of Michigan, and in 1994, he was a member of the planning committee and the overseas coordinator for the Fourth International Conference in Shanghai entitled "Chinese Education for the 21st Century."
David L. Angus died August 14, 1999.
The David L. Angus collection includes material documenting the professional activities of a member of the faculty of the School of Education of the University of Michigan. The collection includes biographical information, files of his writings and conference papers, and papers relating to his interest in comparative education, especially the state of education in China. The collection has been arranged into the following series: Biographical/Personal; Correspondence (1996-1998); University of Michigan School of Education; Course Materials; Writings/conference papers; and Chinese Education.
Subjects:
Angus, David L.; China--History--1976-; Education--Study and teaching.; Education--China.; Education--History.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. School of Education.
Subjects - Visual Material:
One-room schools--United States.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Biographical/Personal
  - Vita (includes vita of wife Anna Wu Angus) (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan personnel information (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan annual personnel report (form Z) (Box 1)
    (includes 1972 grant application to study Britain's open school system)
  - Programs, announcements, clippings (with reference to DLA) (Box 1)
  - Photographs of Aurora brick school house built in1827 (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - 1966-1998, 19 folders (Box 1)
- University of Michigan School of Education
  - Social Foundations and Policy Studies Committee and related 1992-1998, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Bureau of Accredited School Improvement Studies (BASIS)
    - General (Box 1)
    - The BASIS/MASSIP Curriculum Practices Survey 1986-1987 (Box 1)
    - The BASIS/MASSIP Curriculum Practices Survey 1987-1988 (Box 1)
  - Reports on school issues prepared with A. Alfred Taubman and David Monk (Box 1)
  - Michigan's charter schools law and the University of Michigan (Box 1)
- Course Materials
  - Course evaluations (Box 1)
  - Education 392 (Box 1)
  - Education 541 (Box 1)
  - Education 641 (Box 1)
  - Education 791, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Education 792 (Box 1)
  - Education 841, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Writings/conference papers
  The series Writing/Conference Papers consists of reprints and unpublished articles and conference papers mostly relating the history of education, particularly to the development of high schools in Michigan and the Detroit school system.
  - Academic Standards: Historical Perspectives on the Secondary Education/Higher Education Interface (Box 2)
  - African-American School Attendance in the Nineteenth Century: Education in a Rural Northern Community, 1850-1880 (Box 2)
  - The Blueing of the High School: Vocationalism in Grand Rapids, 1900-1920 (Box 2)
  - The Building of an Urban School System: Toward an Ecological Analysis (Box 2)
  - The Changing Status of the Middle Class (Box 2)
  - Class, Politics and the Founding of the Nineteenth-Century American High School (with Jeff Mirel) (Box 2)
  - Common School Politics in a Frontier City: Detroit, 1836-1842 (Box 2)
  - Conflict and Curriculum in the American High School, 1890-1995 (with Jeff Mirel) (Box 2)
  - Conflict Class and the Nineteenth-Century Public High School in the Cities of the Midwest, 1845-1900 (Box 2)
  - Course-taking in Michigan High Schools: The Long-Term Perspective (Box 2)
  - Curriculum and Resource Differences Among Chinese Middle Schools (with Qinghai Chen and Xianglei Chen) (Box 2)
  - Curriculum Planning for the Dropout: Origins of the Excellence/Equity Debate (Box 2)
  - Detroit's "Great School Wars": The School Politics of a Frontier City, 1836-1853 (Box 2)
  - Detroit's Great School Wars: Religion and Politics in a Frontier City, 1842-1853 (Box 2)
  - Does Money Matter": A Study of the Relation Between Financial Differences and School Practice Differences in Michigan High Schools (Box 2)
  - The Dropout in the Post-War Years, 1945-1960 (Box 2)
  - Enrollment Increases and High School Curriculum Reform: Detroit, 1926-1940 (with Jeffrey Mirel) (Box 2)
  - Equality, Curriculum and the Decline of the Academic Ideal: Detroit, 1928-1968 (with Jeffrey Mirel) (Box 2)
  - Equality, Standards, and the American High School Curriculum, 1890-1990 (with Jeffrey Mirel) (Box 2)
  - Ethnicity and School Attendance in the Nineteenth Century: Theory, Comparison, and Analysis (Box 2)
  - An Evaluation of Britain's Open University from an American Perspective: A Report to the School of Education Research Committee (Box 2)
  - Families Against the System: 50 Years of Survival, 1880-1930 (Box 2)
  - The Financing of Basic Education in the US (Box 2)
  - From Spellers to Spindles: Work-force Entry by the Children of Textile Workers, 1890 (with Jeffrey Mirel) (Box 2)
  - High School Course Taking and Educational Reform (with Jeffrey Mirel) (Box 2)
  - High School Curriculum Change in Michigan, 1925-50: Spencer Small Grant Final Report (with Jeffrey Mirel) (Box 2)
  - High Standards for All? (with Jeffrey Mirel) (Box 2)
  - Historical Development of Age Stratification in Schooling (with Jeffrey Mirel and Maris Vinovskis) (Box 2)
  - History of Education and the Computer (Box 2)
  - The Inescapable Institution: Youth, Work, and the Development of the High School, 1850-1950 (Box 2)
  - Inquiry into Historical Methods, Languages, and Literacy (Box 2)
  - The Legitimation Function of Educational Ideas (Box 2)
  - Lies and Damned Lies: The High School Reform Literature of the Early Twentieth Century (Box 2)
  - Mathematics Enrollments and the Development of the High School in the United States, 1910-1994 (with Jeffrey Mirel) (Box 2)
  - Mathematics Enrollments and the Development of the High School in the United States, 1920-1970 (with Jeffrey Mirel) (Box 2)
  - Media, Black Leadership, and the University in the Post-Sputnik Curriculum Debate: Detroit, 1958 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Middle Level Schools: A Special Report (Box 2)
  - Newspapers and Community-Building on the Urban Frontier (Box 2)
  - The Nineteenth-Century Public High School, 'People's College' or a 'School for the Rich': Evidence from Midwest Cities (Box 2)
  - A Note on the Occupational Backgrounds of Public High School Students Prior to, 1940 (Box 2)
  - The Origins of Urban Schools in Comparative Perspective (Box 2)
  - Patterns of Differentiation by Gender and Social Class in a Lighthouse Progressive School District, 1900-1930 (with Jeffrey Mirel) (Box 3)
  - Political Cartoons, Conspiracies, and the American Common School Ideal 1870-1940 (with Jeffrey Mirel) (Box 3)
  - The Politics of Progressive Curriculum Reform: Grand Rapids 1900-1910, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Politics, Race and the Dilution of the High School Curriculum: Detroit, 1930-1968 (with Jeffrey Mirel) (Box 3)
  - Precursors of the American Family Crisis (Box 3)
  - Professionalism and the Public Good: A Brief History of Teacher Certification (Box 3)
  - Quantitative History: Suggestions for Future Research (Box 3)
  - Reassessing Private Schools: Coursetaking Patterns Among Private and Public High School Students, 1900-1994 (Box 3)
  - The Recent Historical & Ideological Background of Education Vouchers (Box 3)
  - Religion and Politics in A Frontier City: Detroit, 1842-1853 (Box 3)
  - Retirement Plans of Michigan School Administrators-A Survey (Box 3)
  - Review: "...Schools and The Means of Education Shall Forever Be Encouraged." (Box 3)
  - Rhetoric and Reform: The American High School Curriculum, 1945-1990 (with Jeffrey Mirel) (Box 3)
  - The Rising Tide of Custodialism: Enrollment Increases and Curriculum Reform in Detroit, 1928-1940 (with Jeffrey Mirel) (Box 3)
  - School Attendance of Rural Blacks in the Nineteenth Century: A Focus on Cass County, Michigan (with Ernestine K. Enomoto) (Box 3)
  - School District Size and Efficiency: The Michigan Record, 1945-90 (Box 3)
  - School Leaving by the Children of Textile Workers, 1890 (with Jeffrey Mirel) (Box 3)
  - School Reform and Economic Theory: The Spokes in the Wheel (Box 3)
  - Schooling & Equality: A Cliometric Approach (Box 3)
  - Secondary Curriculum for the 21st Century: Is Anyone Getting it Right? (Box 3)
  - The Social and Economic Correlates of School Attendance Among the Children of Textile Workers, 1890 (Box 3)
  - Social Class, Curriculum Reform, and the High School Experience: Grand Rapids, Michigan 1900-1920 (Box 3)
  - The Social Consequences of the Introduction of Vocational Education: Grand Rapids as a Test Case, 1900-1920 (with Thomas Neat) (Box 3)
  - Space and Time as Factors in Late Nineteenth Century School Attendance (Box 3)
  - Space, Time, and Compulsion in 19th Century Urban Education (Box 3)
  - Stages in the Development of State Control of Teacher Certification (Box 3)
  - Teacher Education in Research Universities: A Troubled Partnership (Box 3)
  - Teaching Educational History to the Now Generation (Box 3)
  - Toward a New Governance Model: The Committee of Fifteen, the NEA, and the Organization of City School Systems (Box 3)
  - Understanding school choice: What guides and adolescent's decision (Box 3)
  - The University of Michigan as an Educational Leader, 1817-1900 (with Jeffrey Mirel) (Box 3)
  - The Use of the Computer in Educational Management: Recent Developments and the Prospects for Transfer (Box 3)
  - The Uses and Abuses of Comparison in Urban Educational History (Box 3)
  - Value Conflicts in American Education Policy Making: An Excursis on Equity (with Jeffrey Mirel) (Box 3)
  - Value Polarities and Complementaries in American Education Policy Making: An Excursis on Equity (Box 3)
  - Values Clarification: The Professionalization of Life-Planning (Box 3)
  - Vocationalism and the Blueing of the High School: Grand Rapids, Michigan, 1900-1920 (Box 3)
  - Western Perspectives on Pudong N.A. (in Chinese) (Box 3)
  - Youth, Work, and Schooling in the Great Depression (with Jeffrey Mirel) (Box 3)
  - Draft chapter from unidentified book (Box 3)
  - Student papers from Ohio State and later 1956-1965 (Box 3)
- Chinese Education Research
  The Chinese Education Research series includes notes, papers and other material relating to conferences, studies and proposals in which Angus took part.
  - Quantitative methods in Education Research (1988 summer lecture series, Beijing, China) (Box 4)
  - China Secondary School Monitoring and Improvement Program 1988 (Box 4)
    (project submitted to the Henry Luce Foundation's United States-China Cooperative Research Program)
  - Global Conference on New Trends in Science, Technology, Economy and Society (Shanghai, April 4-6, 1990) (Box 4)
  - Seminar on Basic Education and National Development (Shanghai) June 13-15, 1991 (Box 4)
  - Shanghai and Hong Kong (comparative/longitudinal study) 1991 (Box 4)
  - Proposal: designing a school monitoring system/school improvement plan for Zhejiang Province 1988-1991 (Box 4)
  - Educational Research in China circa 1991 (Box 4)
  - Chinese Education for the 21st Century: New Challenges and Prospects in Global Perspectives (4th International Conference; Shanghai) August 15-20, 1994 (Box 4)
  - Human Resource Management Aspects of Pudong New Area 1994, 9 folders (Box 4)
  - Chinese Education towards the 21st Century; Key Issues on the Research Agenda (Hong Kong Special Administrative Region, August 13-19, 1997) 1996-1997 (Box 4)
  - Chinese University of Hong Kong 1997, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence from Chinese scholars (Box 4)